[Music]
all right it's january 28th 2022 and
we're here in actinflab livestream
number 37.0
discussing the paper free energy a
user's guide
welcome to the actin flab we are a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following
good etiquette on livestream
go to
activeinference.org if you want to learn
more about anything happening in actin
flap
all right so today in 37.0
we are going to
learn and discuss and introduce and
provide some background for this paper
free energy a user's guide by stephen
francis mann
ross payne and michael kirchoff and just
like all the dot zeros and discussions
we're just gonna introduce some ideas
give a little tip of the iceberg and
kind of warm up to talk about this paper
in the coming two weeks and so today
we'll be going through a lot of the
background and some of the key
formalisms in the paper
and the coming two weeks we'll be
discussing the paper so let us know if
you want to join
so first there's this comment in red is
this yours dean
yeah
do you wanna yeah
part of me do you wanna describe it here
or in your intro
yeah in the intro great all right well
um we'll each just go around and say
hello and then
i think we can uh just say one reason
why we're excited to discuss it i'm
daniel i'm in california and was just
enticed by the title short and direct
and i think it has some great
solidifications
and perspectives and implications on
multiple levels so
how about stephen
hello i'm stephen i'm based in toronto
um yeah i was interested by
another sort of way to surmise
the free energy principle and active
inference type approaches in relation to
the philosophy of biology
and cognitive science i thought that was
interesting to see how that pitch was
being made
open
hi i'm dean i'm in calgary and
anytime i see the word
guide i'm always curious because of my
background in
setting up programming where people were
going into novel situations so
uh
the authors kind of had me at that word
and then i wanted to sort of learn more
about what they had to say
are some key features of guides or
things that guides should keep in mind
before we head off on this journey
yeah well for me
i've sort of adopted the term wayfinding
kind of as a blanket not just a markup
like but it's a way of maybe describing
what that path could turn out to be
without
necessarily constraining people so
and there i'm sure there are other
descriptions and definitions of the word
guide but that's the one i tend to
to gravitate towards
all right
stephen
yeah and there's also what kind of guide
we end up inhabiting so you know
this biological
grounding it feels like uh
there's a desire to get into our feet
and into the soil somehow
uh as well as the cognitive science so i
feel it's a little bit like i've been
stretched up and
pushed down into the ground so there's
something there
okay
so one big question probably not the
only big question that could be raised
but just the question that approached us
to this paper in some way is how can we
learn and apply active inference
and then dean do you want to talk about
what you wrote here
well i just like to kind of read it out
i don't yes
okay so assuming that making moves
which would we could describe its
behavior now has effects on what happens
next and that those moves are at least
loosely based or inferred on evident
they and the authors use the terms
probabilities predictions
and fitness
so that's in the paper then how might we
begin to look at energy applied
okay and in calculating out our best
guess is measure measurable as or of
what we think or believe will happen
next step on that road to prediction
matter expertise now
prediction matter expertise is a
term i coined and brought up with dr
fristen um
but i think it might
if we're guiding we might
think about that in the background the
other part was they talk about models
and last in our last live stream set
that's all we were doing was talk about
modeling ourselves so it seems like a
natural extension now to talk about
models models as inference and action
models as selection models like as
extenders i.e tools and then how does a
model
curate curated run down help us get
outside the guide
when using energy in ways beyond god
explication and interpretation do we
need a user's guide for the user's guide
which was something i used to ask all
the time
uh the kids that were participating in
the program and that i was setting up
because they were going out with
their background and they had sponsors
who had a different background and we
often wondered whether or not they would
have to give a user's guide to somebody
who was
necessarily more experienced with the
field but not necessarily experienced
with bringing the young person along
so that's why
i think that when we're talking about
how can we learn and apply difference in
this guide theme
those are things we might want to keep
sort of at least partially
in our in our thinking
thanks a lot for sharing that dean a lot
to say but that's what the dot one and
the dot two and beyond are for
so the paper is free energy a user's
guide by steven francis man ross payne
and michael kirkoff it's from the last
days of 21 i believe
and uh it is
on the full-size philsay archive okay so
here are some of the aims and the claims
of the paper
over the past 15 years a novel
explanatory framework spearheaded by
carl firsten has inspired both
excitement and confusion of philosophy
of biology and cognitive science
active inference whose most famous
tenant is the free energy principle
purports to unify explanations in
biology and cognitive science under a
single class of mathematical models
so not math under biology
but
biology under math
there are broadly three reasons why the
active inference framework is difficult
to understand
in the author's words first the
mathematics are are unfamiliar to many
philosophers and even to biologists and
cognitive scientists and
mathematicians and all other kinds of
peoples
second the framework was developed
rapidly by a small but dedicated
dedicated group of researchers limiting
its accessibility while expanding its
scope
recent history
third the framework makes claims across
both mathematical and empirical domains
and the dialectical relationships
between these are unclear
so what is the math bio dialectic who's
nested within who
yes stephen
yeah i think this
the way these three kind of points are
made is is useful for seeing the
rationale for this paper i think there's
seen as a desire to come at
these questions
as if it was coming from
um
people less steeped in all the math
because previous papers might have come
out which had an awful lot of particular
you know particular information that
comes from this dedicated group of
researchers i think by
trying to speak about it
from the perspective of people arriving
it gives those core researchers which i
i know for sure michael kirchoff is you
know
been part of a chance to clarify the
sort of
framings or misconceptions that might
end up
being placed in other papers by
philosophic philosopher philosophers
and i think has become a little bit of a
vicious cycle of
uh and distraction at times and i think
they're maybe trying to reclaim that
ground so that's just my own strategic
guess but it looks like that might be
why this paper's
been been put together well great and
helpful feedback thank you
then the last parts are here we attempt
to redress this situation by targeting
each source of potential confusion so
they're going to identify three
frequently asked questions frequently
raise concerns
underpinning um
frictions and then redress them
and their aim is overall we aim to
increase philosophical understanding of
active inference so that it may be more
readily evaluated
and maybe we could even add um applied
and developed
okay so would either of you like to just
read the abstract
i'll go for it okay over the past 15
years an ambitious explanatory framework
has been proposed to unify the
explanations across biology and
cognitive science
active inference whose most whose most
famous tenant is the free energy
principle
has inspired excitement and confusion
and equal measure
yes it has here we lay the groundwork
for proper critical analysis
of active inference in three ways first
we give simplified versions of its core
mathematical models
second we outline the historical
development of active inference and its
relationship to other theoretical
approaches and third we describe
three different kinds of claim labeled
mathematical empirical in general
routinely made
by proponents of the framework
and suggest dialectical links between
them overall we need to increase
philosophical understanding of active
inferences so that it may be more
readily evaluated
all right
cool so nice and funny abstract we all
laughed
so
the roadmap how do they
structure this guide is it meant to be
read linearly or do you flip to a
different page i don't know but we have
added the page numbers on um on this
slide it's on the bottom right but it'll
be on the bottom left and that's what
page we are in the guide
if as if it were in paper in our hands
and
it starts with an overview
and then there's a discussion on first
the inference of perception or
observations and hidden states and then
action comes into the loop
section 3 gives a brief history of the
free energy principle and section 4
discusses the aforementioned dialectic
of free energy and its rhetorical
ecosystem we could say
that's the part we're not going to focus
on in this dot zero but hopefully we're
gonna be able to go into each of these
really important troikas in the dot one
and two
then there are some concluding remarks
okay
so first how is the word model being
used here it's really good that the
authors included this warning because we
hear about modeling all the time not
just the photography kind the
mathematical kind so they write let us
begin with a warning
the word model takes on two distinct
senses throughout our discussion
the sense more familiar to philosophers
is what we call a scientific model a
representation of some possible or
actual system which a scientist uses to
reason about or discovers features of
that system and related systems
by contrast in the active inference
literature a narrower sense is typically
meant what we will call a generative
model
that's what we're going to be
specifically talking about
this is a mathematical object with
applications in statistics and various
sciences our simplified models of the
free energy principle are scientific
models
so
models is a big category but we're going
to be talking about kind of a narrow
sense of statistical models like linear
regression models but instead of a
linear regression it's a different kind
of model not at the exact same uh
elevation of the linear model or
taxonomy but like in that
category
and then
note further that some scholars opt for
deflationary stance on generative models
using them only to describe the dynamics
of agents so descriptive modeling
it is an open question whether this kind
of model building precludes any form of
scientific realism about the relation
between the model and the target system
these issues are discussed in section
four and also have come up several times
including with most recently majeed beni
but
model-based science and um what does it
mean to use and make models and maps and
territories and all of that so
any thoughts on models because that's
going to be one of the key terms going
forward
what would either of you
say would be the the best way in
layman's terms
to show the difference between what they
mean when they talk about an empirical
model and what they talk about in terms
of a generative model what what sort of
real physical material things could we
use to make clear the difference because
in the last live stream we did a good
job of taking columns
and showing how they were discrete how
would you guys describe this
yes stephen
i think one of the ways this distinction
comes about is is the difference between
most systems type approaches and
non-linear dynamical systems
um generative models are tending to be
coming from
a sort of a swarming it's like a swarm
of bees
creating and evolving
as compared to something which has been
given a perspective
and drawn out somehow in our environment
as in a scientific model
now
the fact that generative models are
being applied in the kind of scientific
way
inverted commas
or are they or they've been
are they being used in a more
instrumental stroke philosophical way
and they can never be fully science
is another question but i think that the
difference there between this kind of
biological
um generative
sort of
process
and something which can be
given a perspective on
and drawn out as a
defined type of model
in a is is where there's a kind of a
clear difference i don't know how others
see that but um
i think that that that also might be
useful
all right dean here be my
answer would be uh two that are on the
extreme end of the yellow type
scientific model would be like the
standard model in physics or
a working model of renal function like
kidney function
so it's like very transdisciplinary and
includes a huge number of domains and
kind of like
logical motifs and has axioms and a
specific history and software toolkits
um and all of that and then
we're going to be talking about like a
kind of model that's basically a
parametric statistical model so like a
gaussian model takes two parameters the
mean and the variance and that can be
written analytically like with equations
or can be done computationally but it's
only ever going to take those two
parameters and it only ever outputs a
certain family of distributions and so
it's like
parameters in distributions out and the
parameters can reflect like the
connectedness of a graphical model too
but you get parameters in
which can include model structure and
then
some type of output but it's
it's close-ended within that paradigm
versus the model of renal function is
like this open-ended question
and i think you hit on something really
really critical there it's distributions
out right so something falls out when
we're talking about a generative model
whereas when we're talking about
something empirical we tend to keep the
focus
stabilized
right like this so the process is is
fundamentally different and so
again when we're talking about in in
sort of layman's terms what the
difference would be
i think you i think you hit the the key
word of that which is something that's
in and stays in versus something that
may start in one place and fall out in a
completely different place with is that
an expectation we should have as a
difference between these two
yeah just one thought then stephen would
be um
both modes are so important it's like
yin yang or left and right hand or
convex and concave um yeah and our
discussions do
move regime of attention from like the
generative model to the bigger question
and in some ways it maps on to
instrumentalism and realism too
but we really need to know when the
pendulum is swung one way and when it's
swung the other way and so we can keep
an open mind and they're all happening
all the time that's both eyes open like
you're always saying dean
but we also um can't
um
go too hard on just one side
so stephen
yeah i think i love what you said though
daniel about the the axioms i think in
generally in science you you try and
have
reproducibility and you have tolerances
and you say how much accuracy and what
says tolerance is on
something but there's a general
recapitulation of similar types of
results again and again and again and
the same sort of thing comes up it has
been there in psychiatry and psychology
you know with with and that's where the
the idea of syndromes being classified
as opposed to symptoms which must be
much more fluctuating more variable so
you could run a generative model
and it can come up with different
results
even with the same input and that
now there will be some kind of
characteristic patterns that generative
models do reveal but that
there is a point where it's quite
different and i suppose when when that
difference i think that's almost
paradigm based difference but maybe
there is some point where they blur i
don't know
yes dean and then we'll go on to the
paper yeah
so at the end of the last live stream
one of the thing comments that one of
our colleagues blew me was that we have
to be able to hold two things up at once
which sang to me because i think that's
what you're saying both of you are
saying right now i think if we look at
if we whether we're looking at a
starling or a
and or murmuration whether we're looking
at an ant or a colony we can keep
something in
inbound or we can have something fall
out from that because it's basic
research like we weren't expecting
something repeatable
that's that's how i would distinguish it
but again i just let's get on to the
paper but i think that's important that
we get that established first if we're
talking about guides
that was the big epistemic disclaimer
and that's what they put in their paper
so we allocate our attention as well
okay so on to the details of the paper
so in two two they introduce this
um
simple model of inference with w and x
so this is figure one there's w for
world
that's the hidden world state and then
there's x the observed data like x marks
the data
and
you can think about like where do you
estimate where the sun is in the sky
that's actually unobserved but then
there's going to be all kinds of
observed data coming in or
we'll talk more about the coming in
versus the generative model later but
the observed data are what are being
modeled as being observed in that sort
of um sensory way
so figure one is the basic model of
inference
the inference problem addressed by the
active inference framework
what other kinds of inference problems
exist what problems do or don't have
this form
what happens if there's no line with w
and x so of course it can get more
elaborate but within this exact format
like w my output x and y
and that'd be like getting two numbers
back in the computer program instead of
or generating two numbers in the
computer program rather than just
returning one
or you can imagine x is like a vector
but we're within
that specific model framework we're not
in the realism of agent environment
we're just in the statistical framework
of a hidden latent variable observable
variable x
the unobservable state is assumed to
cause unobser
assumed to cause observable data
and so this is a little bit of a
connection with dynamic causal modeling
because statistically we call that
causing just like the proportion of
variance explained by a pca
it's like given very active
um terms it's
but it's actually
not causal in the mechanistic sense and
that of course has been to no end of
confusion with how statistical
conclusions are interpreted as
mechanistic
conclusions about the world
and so is it cause
in the sense that we mean it
in one sense or is it associated in a
causal model
and that's kind of the causal and
dynamic causal modeling
that's functional connectivity so that's
the realm that we're talking about not
within the world environment
interaction stephen
yeah this is this is actually
interesting they've gone back to a
pre-markov blanket kind of formulism and
it raises that question then of
what does it mean to infer and it can be
that we infer things because that's what
we get data on so it talks about well
what is it that we can even use to
understand
and what are the assumptions about
what's actually
important
to read and those two things i think
um
this leaves both those things open um
and that that that that actually is a
bit of a bridge between the scientific
and the
uh generative
processes
cool so if we're modeling like height is
not measured but we observed weight and
we're going to do some regression of
like the unobserved and the observed
that is the type of model that we're
going to be talking about loosely and
someone could say oh but this other
factor influences too
yes that's the realism claim this
actually matters in the real world and
it very well may but we're talking about
measured
modeled
relationships stephen
yeah i think this is also really helpful
to be able to look at paradigms because
there's a difference between say the
paradigm of
psychology
from the perspective of looking at
classification
and problem identification and treatment
and coaching psychology
which is about
not so much trying to diagnose what's
there but what sort of actions someone's
trying to take and how you might help
them with those actions to reach
outcomes which may vary
moment to moment and i think
you know in some ways that
that that's this is maybe the level you
have to go back to
because otherwise the noise just swamps
the discussion
it goes deep on both ends that action
orientation the pragmatic turn
ecological psychology is going to
connect deep
and
this is going to be deep but in a sense
narrow because we're just talking about
statistics here so
take statistics courses and learn it
because this is kind of where it comes
from here
okay on to the example of active
caprents that's that's not actually what
they called it but that's the cat
example that we're going to be
discussing
we're going to imagine that you have a
cat animal
that spends its time in either the
kitchen or the bedroom when it's in the
kitchen it often meows for food
when it's in the bedroom it often purrs
loudly suppose you tally the proportions
of the times your cat is in each place
and making each noise the results might
look something like
okay
but the cat also goes somewhere else
okay not in the model or this other
factor or this other sound okay
change the model add another column it's
totally fine it's a fork on the github
or the discussion but
that's the difference between kind of
modifying the model structurally and
using it parametrically within the
narrowest sense of model and then
keeping the discussion alive
about that broader sense like what
stephen is talking about like a model of
psychology or a model of complex
adaptive systems
so one thing to note is that this idea
of setting the prior in a bayesian sense
from observed data
is called parametric empirical base so
parameter parametric we're setting
parameters
like frequencies of things happening and
it's empirical which means observed it
doesn't mean like the only truth it just
means the measured values and then it's
bayesian as we'll talk about
so let's just say 10 or 100 or 10 000
measurements were made and they come out
to these numbers sixty percent um of the
time
they're in the kitchen and forty percent
the cat is in the bedroom and so that's
like summing across that's called the
marginal probability because it was in
the margins of papers and
they
marginals have to sum to 100
because something has to happen in the
model oh but the cat can be in the roots
yes
but within the model it has to be this
way
then that's what makes a probability
then
50 of the time there's meowing and
purring but as the numbers show
the
location
and the sounds
they have a statistical association
there's some divergence that could be
tested for statistical significance
depending on the number of observations
but that is what the numbers in this
table are reflecting
and um
both
uh columns and rows sum up to a
probability so they're all like proper
probabilities
um
[Music]
then how how do you infer about this
like if you were to observe the room how
could you reduce your uncertainty about
what sounds you'd hear
and then if you'd hear sounds how could
you reduce your uncertainty about the
room
many philosophers will be familiar with
one famous method for solving this
problem
bayesian conditionalization
this method can be stated as a principle
saying how an agent using a model p of w
and x w world state hidden x observed
data ought to choose their beliefs q of
w q that's the one we control upon
observing data x what to believe now
conditioned on incoming data
okay any points on that
just they did a really good job of
explaining it
yeah i'm waiting next slide
okay please continue here
so
from the from the actual paper the table
describes a joint probability
distribution which we just explained
uh where w ranges over possible cat
locations either the kitchen bedroom and
x ranges over the possible cat sounds
again very clear straightforward from
the next side usually the science
scientist not the person who
is trying to build a generative model
aims to improve the accuracy of a
generative model of some real-world
world phenomenon which would mean
improving the accuracy of pwx this
learning task is relatively difficult
so i
wanted to kind of parse what relatively
difficult meant and i'm not going to
read all of that stuff there in red
but essentially
what i want to kind of state is
the the authors here said this is simple
don't
don't go to that place of high
complexity quite yet let's just see this
for what it is so that what daniel said
90 seconds ago which was go take a bunch
of statistics courses doesn't have a
bunch of people running off and
screaming into the night
there is there is a complexity to this
but it's not
the kind that will swamp you
but they're basically trying to say is
let's just slowly work our way into this
without every
hit all your historical grievances
around statistics trapping you before
you even really set out set sail
i'll add one note on that this is like
learning how the horse moves in chess or
learning how the castle moves in chess
and so it's possible to get super
connected to your internal life
narrative in the game of chess and
people who would have no problem losing
and connect four or checkers will feel
very engaged emotionally affectively by
chess it just something i've observed
empirically somebody else might have
different priors on that and so this is
a way of just starting with how the
pieces move and then as we're finding
out
playing in a fun we hope
ecosystem and playground and sandbox so
we can figure out how the pieces move
and then we're going to connect them and
do all kinds of fun stuff steven
yeah i think like you say having the
ability to stay with the pieces do lots
of fun stuff look at the the way things
are generating with that data
is different for instance to saying oh
the meowing cat is an assertive cat and
the purring cat is a docile cat which
could be this kind of imposed high order
model and then everything's trying to
fit
to is it a docile cat or is it an
assertive cat
but it's it's flattened out all of this
you know you you loses this ability to
to generate
professor helen longnow has a book
called studying human behavior and
aggression in 2010 that's like once you
define
oh there's a significance difference
between these two groups
or in the count of this behavior per
minute and they've been pre-labeled
it passes the modeling
in the broad sense
into modeling into the narrow sense
we found a difference between the groups
so this is reifying our understanding of
those categories so it's really
important
so this is going to be where the base
enters the picture
the posterior
which means afterwards
is calculated
about how should the distribution p
be updated as new information comes in
so just like the last sentence in red
what's a belief now conditioned on
incoming data so now that is going to be
symbolically or graphically described so
probability the p distribution of world
states conditioned on vertical line new
data coming in
and there's
bayes
theorem
other videos and other
channels and groups will cover bays
better and more comprehensively
but here we can suffice to say that
first we can write it in words
like what's the distribution q that we
control
the probability distribution of us
thinking that it's in the kitchen
that is
the prior probability of it being in the
kitchen condition on it or it's time
conditioned on it meowing so how likely
is it to be given that it me out and
then the numbers that we just looked at
can be plugged in to that verbal
equation and a number is going to come
out
and so we heard meowing and if we just
looked at meowing like four times in the
kitchen one time in the bedroom so four
to five times it was in the kitchen
not the bedroom and then
here's an equation that does literally
that
it just looks at the column and it does
the conditional
likelihood or the posterior of the world
state after the data come in
um
and then there's i think did anyone want
to say anything here there's this
learning task is difficult i think we
already kind of mentioned that so yeah
we yeah yeah and and the whole thing is
is that most people i i think
i'm not gonna say philosophers most
people don't automatically go
to being able to figure out what the
probability is but i think what these
authors are pointing out is there's a
way of being able to show that there is
a probability in play if you are not
certain and this is how you might split
those probabilities out that's all
they're trying to do
okay so now we're going to go from as
we've seen in other papers the sort of
exact bayesian approach most similar
paper to this in this sense is probably
axel constance number 34 with a
bacterium we first looked at the
bayesian bacterium and then we looked at
the variational bayesian bacterium and
then in both cases we looked at how
basically um
[Music]
sometimes new data could come in you
could still make wrong decisions whether
you're doing
exact base or variational inference you
can still make bad decisions as data
come in so this isn't a pangolossian
paradigm this is like a statistical tool
that's already been detached from the
philosophy or at least sort of docked at
shore
and then now also we're
breaking the assumption that it must go
the right way or that it will model real
world systems especially
so again back within the narrow sense
sometimes the specific distribution of
the world states conditioned on data
coming in
is intractable so that distribution
cannot be calculated
this usually happens when the state
space is continuous rather than discrete
which came up on model stream number 5.1
if there's only two decisions left and
right
all you have to do is do two
calculations and then compare which one
is preferable whereas if there's a
steering wheel or a trim tab
then there's an open-ended number
because 87.1 degrees and 87.11 degrees
might be very different in their
long-term consequences so continuous
state spaces are very challenging from a
sensory as well as from an action
perspective
in these cases what is needed is a way
to choose q of w the distribution we
control on the world states to make it
close to
p of w conditioned on x
so
p of world state's condition on data is
the hard one
to compute exactly and this is going to
be choosing a distribution that gets
close to
that other one
when the problem is formulated by
statisticians we usually begin with a
family of possible distributions q and
search for the member of that family
which lies as close to p w condition on
x as possible so just like a linear
model it's like condition on this being
a linear model we're going to find the
best linear model or condition on the
quadratic form we're going to find the
best quadratic form
this is like a little bit more general
conditioned on the family that q is
we're going to do
basically linear regression fitting but
not exactly linear regression
um
how do you make those distributions
converge or align
as best as possible we can do this
also given that a structure has been
chosen this is the fitting part this is
not the structure learning unless the
parameters about structure we can do
this indirectly by using a measure of
inaccuracy
active inference employs a measure of
inaccuracy called variational free
energy labeled f
because it is a measure of inaccuracies
smaller values are better than larger
values so it's like frisbee golf
and the lower the value is the lower the
difference is between the actual p that
you would have calculated perfectly and
q
the way simpler lower dimensional model
that you can control and can save in ram
so that's described here
variational free energy
captures two sources of inaccuracy
that we're going to go into in the next
slides
in belief and dictates how they ought to
be traded off against one another the
two sources which we're going to explore
are overfitting and failing to explain
the data so those will be introduced and
discussed soon stephen
yeah i think this also if we just uh
connect it to that scientific standard
models and this type of work is
this is looking at
contextuality it's like it's like what's
based on where the starting point is
that the probabilities are being
picked up on you start to roll out
the
statistical
results i what sort of meowing is
actually happening
and as opposed to a model where
you're modeling a car engine and you
want to know what energy it's going to
give out this particular moment it's
going to do that whether i'm
watching it or not it's just the same
basic model applies independent of the
observer so i think that's uh
also useful here
yes like getting the model to this stage
like depersonalizes it
in a sense
because that model can be just
transferred and used in a like another
instrument
okay so here's those two sources of
inaccuracy that they described the first
that we're going to discuss is
overfitting
the cost of overfitting they write can
therefore be measured by checking how
far
q the one we control on world states
diverges from p
the first term of f free energy is a
measure of that kind
this
expression two
is also called the relative entry
entropy or holdback library or the kl
divergence
so
this is like the first half of the
two-part equation that will constitute f
and
it looks like this graphically
symbolically but here's a kind of
cool way to think about it
if you were trying to fit a single hump
into this two-hump model in the
empirical distribution
so
you're fitting a family that is going to
get sort of coerced into one of two
extremes
either it's going to end up
fitting one very closely like the higher
one if it's like mode seeking and it
will have no probability density the
blue line
onto the other hump
or
it'll conflate them in a sense into
two
um
uh kind of sub populations blurred
together and have a solution basically
that kind of goes between them
kale divergence
is a way to
fit distributions optimally given this
kind of challenge
which exists for the one hump fitting 2
hump it exists for the 2 hump fitting 3
it exists for the 1 fitting 50. it's a
general statistical problem and kl is a
method that helps bring that blue line
as well as it can on a trade-off
frontier into alignment with the black
one
okay stephen
yeah i suppose this also
gets into the reason when this is useful
is when you're in complex
non-equilibrium situations where things
are fluid
then you're going to hit these
situations and overfitting is quite
common social sciences being one of the
areas where we see these problems
where it's equilibrium based and it's
fairly
clear
then
you don't really have it's not really as
applicable so it sort of speaks to where
this type of approach is applicable i
where there's
this kind of fluid
ambiguity in in this situation
okay thank you
how about the second source of
inaccuracy that is failing to explain
the data
mathematically they write explaining the
data
means assigning high probability to
events w
that make the probability of x high
the penalty for failing to explain data
is captured by the second term of f
which looks like this
um
higher terms of
the actual value
are matched with high value um with high
values on the distribution we control q
to keep this term low so this is kind of
like if it were a linear regression and
all the data points were lined up and
the line just went right through them
then it would be doing really well on
explaining the data
and that would be given a low score here
whereas if that weren't the case it'd be
flipped dean
so when i was doing my work i didn't
have
access or maybe i wasn't looking hard
enough for the kl divergence so i can
remember even on here and some of these
live streams saying i have no idea what
that even means i have a better idea now
but is
one of the metaphors that i tried to use
was in terms of avoiding overfitting or
failing to be able to explain the data
was so all those horizontal and vertical
lines creating a mesh
acting as a filter
how far apart do we set those what gauge
do we set our mesh for in terms of what
we want to have stay above the mesh and
what's passing
passing through now again maybe that's
not sophisticated enough for a lot of
philosophers but to get the basic point
down
that's the kind of example i had to
provide
to be able to give people some sense not
just that these lines are now
rigid
and the 20s on this percent and the 40
is on this percent and
never tell shall the two pass again but
the lines actually move
thanks a lot so you're so
right about that the example with the
active cat friends and the variational
cat friends is like discrete by discrete
is four quadrants
so in some ways that's like the simplest
model
right it could be two continuous
variables it could be like the volume
and then the cat's position on the
x-axis in a room now imagine if it was
the x and the y i was continuous or
something like that but just even two
continuous variables and you're totally
pointing out where it's like you're
gonna
put the points around whether you put
them right in the middle of the four
quadrants
or whether it's more scatter shot or
something in between
and then there's two parameters there's
like a linear regression through the
points
and then there's how fine the mesh is
and you're observing like pixel
densities and doing a regression through
the pixel densities and so you could
have a super continuous situation it is
a continuous variable inside the bedroom
but then in the model we just looked at
it's in one quadrant
and we talked about that when we talked
about um serval's paper and how it was
just the park and the cafe and yes
there's locations within the park but
they weren't within our model
so we didn't deny the reality of that
physically we just we're modeling
statistically something specific
okay stephen
i mean this the filtering could also be
relating to
the sort of temporal sampling rate
because if you're measuring every
millisecond
if it's meowing or not it becomes
pointless there's a kind of a
making sense
rate at which the um
the entropy is being converged at and
and as we know in the brain we seem to
have multiple
levels of that
okay awesome
next few ones we're going to go through
just kind of quickly and specifically
so let's put those two terms together
this
is the overfitting and the over
and the failing to explain the data
variational free energy f
the non-metaphysical version
is the sum of the penalties for
overfitting and failing to explain the
data it's those two terms that we just
described
added together
so that the best explanation
in a sense
is the lowest on both of them
it's not over fit
it fits it well and it doesn't do it any
more than that so you know simple as
possible but no simpler or any other
number of quotes that's kind of this
equations it's not the only way it could
be written it's not the only thing that
fulfills that process but it's something
that can be used and it's very tractable
as it turns out
um
this
free energy has tractable
computation
13.
page 14. so
now it's possible to actually use that
tractable approximation
and
do decision making
and here is where they have the decision
making
here argman means choose the
distribution q that makes the following
term as small as possible
so this is where
f
goes from kind of being like a um a set
of pipes with nothing really running
through it
to
a specific finite set of tested
alternatives those are affordances in
the case of action selection
they're discrete in the case of a
discrete inference like is it in the
bedroom or is it in the kitchen it's
continuous in the case of a continuous
inference problem like how bright is it
outside on a continuous scale
but even for continuous things sometimes
we just do one through ten or one
through 100 or one through 1024
so discrete state spaces are really
important even if there is a continuity
to the world so those are the kinds of
computations that variational inference
helps perform
it takes something that's descriptive
and moves it into a decision-making
imperative just like the l2 norm or
least-squares is like a decision-making
imperative for linear regression
this is like an imperative for model
fitting
in
this framework
um
the free energy principle the form here
inference is the same as that of
bayesian principle discussed earlier
in both cases you perform a calculation
and set q of w equal to the resulting
value
the difference is that bayesian
principle cancels a direct calculation
via bayes theorem in contrast free
energy principle cancels what might be
called an indirect calculation
happily in practice this can be done by
trial and improvement rather than trial
and error
so that's
axl constants bacteria the bayesian and
the variational bacterium
combined with
going to the bottom of the bowl on the
smooth gradient descent landscape with a
straight arrow utility and the
solenoidal epistemic component
various algorithms for finding q the
distribution we control are available
depending on the details of the
generative model classic citation that
gets
referred to a lot
one of the developments that prefigured
active inference
was the implementation of such an
algorithm in a neural network first in
2005.
old citation classic
we're seeing that again
in model stream 5 in
alex chance's work and of many others
that this format
even long before active inference
brought it onto the scene in our
little side stage
using neural networks to fit variational
bayesian methods
was a common technique in machine
learning stephen
so when we say trial and improvement
rather than trial and error it's
basically saying
that the error can be used and utilized
in an ongoing way it's not like you have
to start from scratch and come up with
another
attempt from scratch you're
you know you're using
what it the same basic architecture and
just keep running
it's so true i never really thought how
demoralizing trial and error was
like how should we get stronger oh well
you're going to try and then you're
going to fail
when error is perceived as a failure
naively but trial improvement would be
like we're going to try and we're going
to improve
so
yes of course error is implicit in that
dean
yeah and i'm glad you used the bowl
analogy because one of the things that i
read and i was actually on the
highlighted trial and improvement thing
because
for example if you had the bowl filled
with water and a ping-pong ball floating
on top
and you had to drill a hole because you
wanted the ping pong ball to settle at
the bottom of the bowl at a certain time
you could you could continuously improve
by adding more holes of a certain
diameter until you were able to get that
flow rate and have that ping pong ball
arrive at the bottom of that bowl at the
particular time at the discrete time
that you were looking for that's not an
error thing that's just a we'll continue
to get a little bit closer and closer
we'll we'll figure out what the dosage
is and i agree with you a lot of people
think it that the basic research part of
it is oh i failed no a lot of this stuff
is
i test it and then i test it again and
then i oh i came really really close so
now the difference is really low which
is what these authors are talking about
all right i'm just going to continue on
because we do have a ton more to do so
that's still on the perception side
we're not talking about where we're
going to go walking we're talking about
the sound of the cat and where the cat
is located in the infants and so we're
still within this empirical variational
catfence area
this is the bull
this is
fitting that distribution the conjoint
distribution that's the free energy
distribution
and that is the one that's bowl like
so here is the variational free energy
of the black line and it's basically
the com composition of two factors
penalty for overfitting and the penalty
for failing to explain the data and each
of those have a certain distribution
underneath them in this setting
so
their combination is like f plus g of x
it's like h of x it's just adding
functions together so it's just another
cost fitting function
for the really specific kinds of models
that we're talking about here
let's bring in action
so now it's still the same case of w and
x going to the agent now notice that the
agent wasn't drawn in the previous model
it was just w to x
so that was um probably graphical as
well as somewhat of a conceptual
simplification like i mean these
measurements it shouldn't matter who's
observing them right oh wait
quantum it does
but now the agent can also take action z
so z is going to be the whole question
of control theory and cybernetics and
action
the previous section dealt with
inference rule how to choose q of world
states beliefs on world states this
section is about acting
now suppose you can perform an action z
that will place the cat in one of two
rooms by changing the hidden state w
you can indirectly change future values
of x or at least change their
proportions or their likelihood
so decision rules stem from measures of
preference because if you don't know
where you're going you're lost or if you
don't care about the two things then it
doesn't really matter
one of the confusing aspects of active
inference is that it treats the
statistical model p
the one that is the actual distribution
we're trying to get close to and this is
like the key point that we'll be
returning to for our whole life
that model p
is a measure of both probabilities and
preferences at the same time
and that's going to be what we continue
to talk about because it's one of the
most important points that this paper
makes clear in a way that other papers
um
haven't really
perhaps harped on in exactly the same
way
let's look at figure 3 again
look at the yellow part octave inference
employs a controversial dual
interpretation
of p of w probability of world states
and probability of
observations as probability
distributions and preference
distributions over hidden states and
sensory states specifically
dean with the red text
again i don't want to take up a bunch of
time because we're having one of the
authors or a few of the authors on we
can probably pull this out a little bit
but for now
that when we when we introduce
preferences
and probabilities
it isn't just a second
it isn't just a second consideration it
can almost run away from us really
really quickly if we're not really
careful in terms of
pulling back on the reins a little bit
and really thinking about what does that
imply so i'll just leave that for there
for now
great point thanks for sharing it
succinctly
they write recall that free energy
principle inference counsels choosing
beliefs by minimizing a function that
measures the cost of inaccuracy and
that's because the free energy
calculation includes both of those
variable uh features the overfitting
penalty and the failure to explain
penalty
action selection is governed in the same
way as inference remember we were
talking only about inference when we
were talking about the variational
methods
now there's going to be a twist
a slightly different cost function
called the expected free energy so
that's why we were previously just
talking about the f variational free
energy now we're going to be talking
about g expected free energy
labeled g
the definition of g is closely related
to that of f
the interpretation of the two penalty
terms changes
as the formalism is updated to reflect
the fact
we are now making measurements over
expected future states
so this is not just measurement error
there's the fundamental unknowingness of
the future since teacher states have yet
to be observed the agent must average
over them to obtain
expected values
the penalties are associated with
failing to satisfy preferences
and failing to minimize future surprise
overfitting
preferences
failure to explain
surprise
expectation
preferences preferences when now or then
let's look at how those play out in this
sort of
action selection through variational
free energy
through time aka the expected free
energy formulation
and how those two pieces
satisfying preference failure and
failure to minimize future surprise look
now but this is sort of the
elaboration or the cousin of this one
this is like snapshot inference
and now we're going to be looking at
expectations through time
um
okay so first filling to satisfy
preferences so again keep that simpler
version in mind this is going to be a
slightly different one in six they even
right
compare equation two
um
this is
make uh i hope failure uh failing to
satisfy preferences given a clear enough
term but it totally brings in something
different which is
something about the agent as dean wrote
so there's big implications of course
because there can't be a non-preference
driven action selection
in any useful sense
whereas the variational one was just
like given the scatter i want the best
mesh and regression
that one it does embody implicit
assumptions about the world and so on
but this takes it to a whole another
level
and here's where that controversial dual
interpretation comes into play
not only is it unusual to treat p as a
preference distribution
it is unusual to treat the goal of
decision making to produce a
distribution that matches that
distribution rather than maximizing
expected utility
so you don't need a preference
distribution other than more
for reward learning
whereas here we're trying to realize our
preferences
and match distributions rather than
maximize for minimizing the divergence
from
these
realistic but
optimistic
expectations so perhaps it is best to
keep in mind that preference in this
sense might mean something different
than utility in the traditional sense
stephen
yeah without going back into that but
the
whole point of
having this matching um distributions
rather than
um expected utility which effectively
again becomes kind of like
equilibrium states places where things
settle and can be measured and they're
kind of stable
you're in this kind of realm of
a more fluid flux type process so i
think that's that's one thing and i
think the other one is
um this
focus on the future the focus on
predicting and things
going into the future and how to make
sense of that rather than looking back
and trying to which is often what
science is doing is and explain
retrospectively
in the same way psychology
is often trying to explain what it sees
before it and coaching psychology is
trying to
see what can be done
to get closer to something that's more
suited
great point thank you it really embodies
the forward-lookingness rather than the
optimal reward or prediction on previous
observations all right so failure to
minimize future surprise this is the
other term failure to satisfy
preferences
now failure to minimize future surprise
formalism seven
one of the tenets of active inference is
that asians should act this is in a
normative
stance to ensure that future data are
not too surprising
and so here is the formalism as written
this is the failure to minimize surprise
in addition to conditionalizing on z
z is action
so
we know that the vertical line is
conditioning on and then z are the
affordances like the action states in
this simple example we're not going to
go into the markov to the policy into
the action state yet this is from the
simpler cybernetic or sort of
agent environment framing that doesn't
distinguish that as clearly but z is
just an action
that the agent engages in
the failure to minimize future surprise
is conditioned on z
so it's not that there's some sort of
world that we're not altering and then
we're doing some strategy in that in
alterable world
leading to this total ad hoc way of
integrating the outcomes of action into
the niche
the world states in the future have
expectations that must be calculated as
expecting on policy selection
so it's not just that some policies have
effect and some don't it's that the
inference of
the future failure to minimize surprise
is conditioned statistically in the
algorithm on the choices
now when that includes choices about
beliefs
doesn't it get so interesting
so
that is one of the cool parts about this
calculation
um and then
this expected free energy oh okay steven
yes scott
that also brings in an element of this
contextuality it's it's it's what sort
of choices
were made then
in context
x or well let's not use
that context right it's important and
it changes things and you can't do that
if you're taking averages
um
and sort of pre-built models
okay so now just like we kind of looked
at the two parts separately and then
summated into
f the variational free energy and then
looked at those two parts here
we've gotten to equation eight in the
paper
which is g
which is
a function of those two distributions p
and q as well as action and here are
those two pieces that we just discussed
and then they write the third input to g
g
is z rather than x
so not observations but action
as mentioned above this is because we
are calculating the expected value over
possible future sensory states
rather than inferring on the basis of a
sensory state that has just occurred
okay so that's exactly what steven said
f is really good for sensory inference
it's about giving the just observed
sensory data what the estimate of the
world should snap to
but action
is totally different not just because it
entails preferences like dean raised but
also because the consequences of action
in the future are unknown
so
the distribution for
planning as inference for action as
inference rather than for perception as
inference
needs to require conditionalizing on
action not on sense
even though sense does come into play
it's a little bit like hidden away
here's the what we're getting at which
is the sensory distribution noticeably
not here but on the right side only
and then
the function that we're minimizing on is
action inference active inference
as with f the measure g suggests the
principle free energy principle in terms
of action not as inference
is minimizing the free energy on action
selection
that can be read as an approximation of
not optimal bayesian sensing
but optimal bayesian design of
experiments and optimal bayesian
decision theory
dean
and i think right here is i'm just
pausing for one second
i think that we're going to get into
some more
evidence of this but i think this is the
first moment when we can say
active inference and free energy well
not free energy active inference
does not necessarily constrain itself to
being just a framework it's actually a
filter as well
because of the active part
it's not stable it's constantly
being updated
because of that active piece and the
preference piece so we could call it a
framework but i don't think we're doing
it justice there's a framework aspect to
it and there's a filtering piece to it
and so that's why i talk about search
fields all the time so i just want to
drop that seed now so that when the
authors come on we can talk about that a
little bit more in terms of the context
that stephen mentioned about guiding
awesome thank you
so now we're going to return to the
active cat friends
so let us present a solution to the cat
example
for the problem to have a determinate
solution we need the conditional
distribution world state's condition on
action z
that means that the consequences of
action have to be estimated if we put
the cat in the kitchen it usually stays
there so this is again the two pieces
that action introduces into the puzzle
is the question of preference otherwise
why bother
and the question of the consequences of
action so the red is a statement that's
empirically observed
from observed data about what happens
what happens when you are estimating
location conditioned on action this is
that q of w conditioned on z
and so you can see when it goes into the
kitchen it stays in the kitchen nine out
of ten times whereas if it puts in the
bedroom after some period of time like
steven brought up not one millisecond
later but one hour later one minute
later it's model specific
it's time scale friendly it's not time
scale free
and then you can compute
numbers
having to do with action selection
within this model
it is worth restating how unusual it is
to interpret p as a measure of both
probabilities and preferences but i mean
it's the letter p
there's nothing wrong with treating a
distribution as a measure of preferences
distributions don't demand to be
interpreted as probabilities after all
but what is unorthodox
in what church and in need of
justification is giving the very same
mathematical term two different
interpretations within the same equation
so that's the two eyes at once kind of
looking back
and then they go into a little bit more
detail about what that actually means
we are not aware of proponents of active
inference taking this interpretive line
but it appears to be a viable option so
just awesome
and clear
writing and drawing something out
through
the re-understanding and the
communication
which happens synchronously and
asynchronously
one of the ways proponents of the
framework turn to this unusual
interpretation to their advantage is by
casting action as a form of inference so
here's from a buckley citation
and that's why it's called active
inference
and we just kind of talked about it a
little earlier so the mechanism
underlying minimizing expected free
energy is formally symmetric to
perceptual inference
formally symmetric
overfitting failing to satisfy
preferences failure to explain the data
failure to minimize expected surprise on
future data that's why it's the only one
that has the x in there
rather than inferring the cause of
sensory data an organism must infer
actions that best make sensory data
accord with an internal representation
of the environment
statistical representation not the
debate on whether organisms have
representations
2.4 simple model of selection
this is where the markov blanket is
going to enter in our model x and z are
the inputs and outputs of the agents x
observations z actions
the set x and z is the agent's markov
blanket
the term is derived from judea pearl's
work on inference using bayesian
networks pearl 1988 classic citation
other live streams
we talk more about marco blankets so
we're not going to go into it too much
more here but it's definitely the tip of
an iceberg if you want to check out more
but here
in the sense required here
a mark out blanket can be understood as
the set of nodes that screen off the
agent from nodes considered external to
it
screen off the agent or screen off the
internal states of the statistical model
another toy model will help illustrate
consider an agent whose surface
temperature
x can safely lie between negative four
and four units
temperature's continuous okay
but it's a discrete model
and so here death is coming into the
picture on either end too hot and too
cold
so this is going to be like variational
cap friends but now it's a freezing and
a burning end of the room and the cat
or the robot cat is going to be making
decisions about what to do so the
external world state is w the
temperature
and then the perception is going to be x
the observation
notice that the value of w does not
affect the agent's preferences so the
preferences for living or for
homeostasis or whatever regardless of
the observations in that snapshot moment
but not precluded over longer time
skills all the agent directly cares
about is its surface temperature denoted
by x that's why the two rows are
identical
so these are sort of the observations
and
the different um actions that can be
taken to move between
um one end and the other perceiving only
the temperature
the agent tries to guess how to act how
to stay within its expected range
and then this is sort of the intuitive
pseudo code when the temperature is high
you want to go towards the lower end
when the temperature is low you want to
act to go towards the higher end
and so here is like the simple example
this is kind of like the bacteria that
has the right priors versus the one
that's just deciding randomly or without
any
resemblance of relationship to the other
observations and so here is the smart
agent
that's just keeping its free energy
every time it gets up as it moves away
it acts to bring it back down into
alignment
and then here's um the agent's control
over its external state is 95 percent
accurate so five percent of the time it
slips and then that's what they say it's
grasp slips the optimal control the
handle
has been lost because of a motor
ineffectuality but that can be recovered
whereas the randomly acting or just sort
of like the sort of brownian
walk
diffusion process ends up um dying
okay dean
uh all i was gonna say here is is
did it create did a great explanation
and if this was your first encounter
with the w
and the zed
and the x
you'd have to really really slow this
down
because the first time you encounter it
it's it it takes more than one pass you
might have to go over it a third and a
fifth and a seventh time for it to
actually make sense because there is we
all have a certain capacity in terms of
the amount of variables we can juggle at
once
and i was when i first looked at this it
it made sense to me but i could sense
from somebody who's maybe coming from a
philosophical background
and not necessarily having the same
degree of statistical
um
hands-on experience as maybe the three
of us do this would be a moment where
you really want somebody to hold your
hand
that's what
community and active lab is for
because then it can be like an
interaction and every question is
welcome so as long as there's attention
in the game
everybody's gonna make it stephen yeah
so this also does give an indication
that
with
variational free energy
having some sort of perturbations can be
useful
particularly if you had multiple
um parallel kind of sources of
information
being integrated
it so having some noise is a good thing
right it's not it's actually gives you a
way to start to make inferences one
question is there
that on the left there's no real
learning happening
but it still makes it even without the
learning component still is more stable
um yes it's not doing parameter updating
it's just like
um a previously learned association
between the temperature and the
direction to move
and also notice like the observation of
sensory is assumed to be perfect here so
there's many layers which can be brought
in but this is kind of like the kernel
motif
okay
the correspondence between
high values of f
and life-threatening states lead to a
third form of the free energy principle
so we had inference and action
perceptual inference then we had action
selection and here is free energy
principle selection
any system that survives long enough
will act so as to appear to be
minimizing f
that's the first time we got any
discussion of far from equilibrium
thermo
thermodynamics of anti-dissipative
systems resilient systems anticipatory
systems
except indirectly through action but
this is the sort of selective
darwinian
side of fep
okay of course there's a ton that could
be said here
this is not a normative principle not a
suggestion to agents regarding how they
should perform inference but a means of
describing how agents behave
axl's paper
minimizing free energy is not living
alone but living systems will be those
that appear as if they've minimized free
energy
and then here i think someone wrote i
just wrote that in there because yeah
that's going to tell you what your
autobiography is going to sound like
given that you're still alive and can
write one
yep um my last words are
in recent work firstin gives a
deflationary interpretation on which
agents do not in fact minimize anything
but perform acts which can be
interpreted as minimizing f
so c
live stream number 34 0 1 2 3.
that is the reason for the emphasize
phrase so as to appear to be minimizing
f
that's
deflationary instrumentalism
highlight
despite this deflationary approach there
is a link between this and the earlier
principle
agents subject to the free energy
principle of inference perceptual
inference ought to minimize f
so if this is ought is tied to their
survival then the normative principle
has the same underlying justification as
the descriptive principle
so this is sort of i don't know if it's
been noted before but basically it's
equivalent to saying the evolutionary
ought is an is
so it's kind of like not from
the fitness side the malthusian
darwinian side
but from the anti-dissipative side
this is how things have looked it's like
saying fitness isn't necessarily
being projected into the future but if
you do do the computations fitness can
be assigned to like different single
nucleotide polymorphisms that have had
different success and you will only see
successful ones but it's a bit more
complex than that in the moment
so here are the three piece the tale of
three piece we have the tale of two
densities what other what other jokes
have we had
in each of the three examples discussed
in a section there's been a distinct
role for the distribution p and a
distinct interpretation of each model
narrow sense
in our first model p was a generative
model employed by an agent it was
therefore interpreted as representing
probabilities
like where the cat is
but now in order to introduce action in
a meaningful way we had to have
preference like i want the cat to be in
the kitchen
so when we brought action into the game
we had to
introduce preference
what makes active inference
similar but also different from other
frameworks
probabilities and preferences are
represented by p
in addition to representing
probabilities in the second model p
measured the desirability of certain
future states over others
i expect you to go to school every day
that's something having to do with
action
if it's serious
it was therefore interpreted as
representing preferences
in our third model p tallied the
historical frequencies of a set of
hypothetical ancestors
fitness it was therefore interpreted as
representing the fitness of different
states
so supporters of the framework often
point to the third role
fitness
ph
to explain how p can simultaneously
fulfill the first two
it's like if that thermal bacteria
is
rocking its niche
it will have high fitness
okay
so
that is
where the three p's get us
here's just a brief look forward so for
any of these next slides we're not going
to go into the actual
very nicely fleshed out arguments
themselves but stephen or dean just
raise your hand if either of you have
anything to add on like each of these
section headers so
um
section 2.5 is extensions to the model
more things to learn more ways to act
we've seen adjectives added to active
inference
deep
sophisticated
contrastive
affective
what other adjectives have we seen
that's sort of this section of the
guidebook it's like there's your um usb
port
what can you have added into it or how
can it be developed
and so that's where we see sort of the
adjectival
family of something active inference
maybe even n active inference
coming more into the philosophy side but
also there's all the elaborations that
we've seen of the actual parametric
model in the narrow sense
sometimes it's in both camps like
affective inference
has to do with
a model derivation or metacognition
as well as something about like the
model in a bigger sense
but
we can recognize both those lanes at
once stephen
yeah i mean one other one's inactive
inference uh reciprocal active influence
there's a couple more like that that's
definitely uh
definitely true just one thing i was
gonna throw in i noticed they talked
about this and it's i know it's in the
quote but they talk about any system
i always wonder whether that's a bit of
a
that a little bit of a
piece of paving stone waiting to be
tripped over um
because i kind of feel like you know i
if you're going to say it maybe any
nonlinear dynamical system
or nested systems of systems or things
uh i just always think that
that that can be a little bit of a a
hazard yeah it inherits a lot of the
legacy ambiguity around system like
you've brought up a bunch of times so
it's really helpful so
in section three
notice how the history brief history of
the free energy principle comes after
what we just spent the last
hours and pages on
so it isn't a history of science
perspective but it is being recognized
as important and so the free energy
principle is a modern incarnation of
ideas that have been raised sporadically
over at least the five decades
it combines traditions from physics
biology neuroscience and machine
learning and other areas especially
the modifications and increasingly the
applications and it's a bi-directional
freeway it's not just two lanes in both
direction
it's going both ways
so this is sort of the history which is
fun because it's a
recent history in some
parts
okay
section four
moves from the historical to the
philosophical so section four dialectic
the free energy principle and related
claims
mathematical empirical and general
claims section 4.1
this is where all that mathematics
groundwork
pays off because in the author's words
we think a great deal of confusion can
be overcome by considering three kinds
of claims
first there are mathematical claims
those were the ones that were just
brought up in earlier sections
so that's the theorems the scientific
models and the statistical techniques in
the more narrow sense
and by doing good scholarship we show
that the core features absolutely
predate active inference and there's
less controversial than some might
suspect
however christian colleagues have since
introduced many novel mathematical
elements
like the perception and action
interpretation on the markov blanket
importantly claims in this category do
not need to be interpreted as statements
about real systems in order to be
evaluated so part one is its
instrumentalism part two is separate the
parts that predate active inference from
some of these more recent derivations
even within the only technical area
second area of confusion
or the second way that confusion can be
overcome by considering another kind of
claim
is
partitioning off you know we're going to
add like a line here from that
mathematical everything that was in the
section that we just discussed plus
stuff that was more recent like 32
there are empirical claims about
cognitive and biological systems how
brains and bodies actually work
these are the remit of cognitive
neuroscience and biology
so those are empirical biological claims
third are general claims that typically
abstract across a wide range or by class
of empirical claims so that's like the
sort of
everything nested systems collective
behavior angle so
separating those and maybe there's more
is really helpful because sometimes
people say well this general claim is
true because look at how this in the
skin works well what about the skin well
that look at how the math works and why
does the math work that way because of
the general claim is that an argument
what is the justification
and the links among these dialectical
categories
well if there's three kinds of claims
mathematical empirical in general then
there are all the edges of that triangle
if you had a fourth one you'd have all
the edges of a tetrahedra and then you'd
almost have a model
the mathematical to empirical direction
invites philosophical analysis due to
novel interpretations of scientific
model terms
so how can math be used to justify
empirical claims
why does equations have anything to do
with what people say about the brain and
the body in the niche
why is that justified at all
other than just other people in their
epistemic authority have done it or it's
how it has been done stephen
instrumentalism also it gives a kind of
a bridge between
realist science and applied science
um and it's kind of sitting somewhere
between the two
um
so i think that's uh
that's quite a useful piece that this
adds to this it's an equation
nice
and then the last two edges of that
triangle
are how can mathematical not both
directions on each edge
you could add but how can mathematical
claims justify general claims
well how could you say that about nested
systems about nested markov blankets
the math
okay
that's important to investigate
and how can general claims justify
empirical claims how could you say that
about the ants well
fitness or dissipative systems so how
can general systems claims
justify anything about empirics so those
are some of the edges
of these three kinds of claims and
there's also claims and subclaims which
is why it's really important to have
rhetorical ecosystem mapping
and an ontology for active inference so
that we can actually
learn and apply across languages and
through time stephen
yeah and i think also we can think of
this as
structural and functional
insights being gained rather than
necessarily repeatable
measured
outcomes every time being gained so
there's an idea that these insights
might reveal something about the
structure or the functionality of the
dynamics
knowing that no one simulation
may ever be repeated quite the same way
particularly if it's got a fair few
variables
yes
so the concluding remarks
the active inference framework is
incredibly ambitious
is it the framework or the people in its
explanatory scope
from humble beginnings as a theory of
brain function it is now positioned as a
framework for understanding life itself
there is a critical tradition in the
philosophy of biology inspired by
richard levins
with regard to such ambitions
many
then
will approach active inference with
skepticism healthy skepticism is a good
thing but healthy skepticism is informed
skepticism unfortunately getting one's
head around the details of active
inference is no small task
our goal in this introduction has been
to clarify the basic mathematics
history and internal dialectics of
active inference
in that order those were the sections
and draw attention to some key concerns
with these details on the table
philosophers of biology are in a better
position to critically evaluate the
framework we look forward with interest
to seeing the results
classic future looking last sentence
so
that's the final lines
we have a ton of things to discuss in
37.1 and 2. it'd be awesome to have any
of the authors as well as any other
people who just want to jump on for a
returning or a first time discussion
but we'll close
under the buzzer in the third period i
know that's how they count up there dean
so
any final comments on uh just
what you're looking forward to
discussing
dean first because you never get the
last word and then stephen
yeah i don't want the last three so
one of the things i want to talk about
in that point one is that the general
claims because i get to trot out one of
my favorite parables that i made up
which is three functions walk into a bar
and i want to be able to because i get
lots of mileage out of that and whether
it's three functions or it's probability
preference and fit
the same holds true it can be great
taste and less filling so i want to have
a look at that because i think that
really tags on to the idea that what
they're talking about here in terms of a
guide could also set us up really well
for creativity and then i also want to
be able to say that that creativity
isn't because we're framed in but
because we can filter as well
three interpretations of a function walk
into a bar
stephen
yeah i'm really curious about how
especially if we speak to the authors
these first principles of hidden states
and inferences and which ones are
selected and which data is available to
actually make inferences on can be used
um particularly for me the example of
psychology versus coaching psychology
and that type of paradigm shift
awesome yeah i really appreciated um
both of your perspectives on this paper
um it really shows how different life
experiences can be
in conversation with some of the
technical details so thank you both and
for everybody who's watching and
participating
see you around the lab see you in the
upcoming weeks 4.1.2
peace thanks guys bye
you